<sequential display_name="First sprint">

  <vertical display_name="Introduction" url_name="first_sprint_introduction">
    <html url_name="first_sprint_introduction_1">
      <p>
        Now that you're all set and ready to go, let's get prepared for your first sprint!
      </p>
    </html>
  </vertical>

  <vertical display_name="Expectations" url_name="first_sprint_expectations">
    <html url_name="first_sprint_expectations_1">
      <p>As a newcomer you should:</p>
      <p></p>
      <ol>
        <li>
          Not commit to more than <strong>3 points</strong>
          of tasks during your first week, or 5 points your second week
          (so 8 points in a two-week sprint).
          It's really easy to over-commit at first, so keep your commitments manageable.
          If you finish early you can always ask in the
          <a href="https://chat.opencraft.com/opencraft/channels/sprint-planning"><em>Sprint planning</em></a>
          channel whether someone needs any help,
          and take on more work later in the sprint.
        </li>
        <li>
          Provide lots of updates to your assigned reviewer/mentor for each task,
          so they can provide timely help.
        </li>
      </ol>
    </html>
  </vertical>

  <vertical display_name="Sprint planning agenda" url_name="first_sprint_sprint_planning_agenda">
    <html url_name="first_sprint_sprint_planning_agenda_1">
      <p>
        Please read
        <a href="http://opencraft.com/doc/handbook/sprint_planning_agenda/" target="_blank">Sprint planning agenda</a>
        to see the agenda for our weekly meeting.
      </p>
    </html>
  </vertical>

  <vertical display_name="Task tracker" url_name="first_sprint_task_tracker">
    <html url_name="first_sprint_task_tracker_1">
      <p>
        Please visit the JIRA task tracker, especially the
        <a href="https://tasks.opencraft.com/secure/RapidBoard.jspa?rapidView=5&amp;amp;view=detail" target="_blank">Weekly sprint</a>
        and look at some of the tickets on the board, to get a feel
        for the type of tasks awaiting you in the near future.
      </p>
    </html>
  </vertical>

  <vertical display_name="Point estimates" url_name="first_sprint_point_estimates">
    <html url_name="first_sprint_point_estimates_1">
      <p>
        Please participate in the grooming session (point estimation) that
        the team does at the end of each sprint.
        Usually you should get an email about this and can follow the link
        to reach the estimation page, but if not, try
        <a href="https://tasks.opencraft.com/projects/OC?selectedItem=com.spartez.jira.plugins.jiraplanningpoker:pokerng-project-side-panel-link&amp;rapidView=5&amp;source=sidebar" target="_blank">this link</a>
        to see if you have been invited to any session. When grooming, you
        don't have to provide a number of points for every issue (or even
        most) - put '?' if you don't feel you have enough knowledge to
        estimate a task.
      </p>
    </html>
  </vertical>

  <vertical display_name="First assigned task" url_name="first_sprint_first_assigned_task">
    <html url_name="first_sprint_first_assigned_task_1">
      <p>Your first sprint contains a lot of challenges that you were not prepared to face. One of these challenges is
        deciding which task to pick and whether the picked tasks suits your experience and what you're looking to
        achieve in OpenCraft.
      </p>
      <p>During this period, don't forget that your assigned mentor (the "Reviewer 1" on your onboarding task) is
        expected to be very present and proactive during the assignation of tasks, and it would be good to pick them
        together. You are free to pick a selection of tasks suggested by the mentor. However, make sure that
        you really picked the right tasks for you. If your mentor hasn't yet worked with you to find a task (or two)
        for your first sprint(s), please ask them to do so.
      </p>
      <p>
        We would like to emphasize here that the mentor is only an adviser, and ensuring that you take on an
        appropriate workload is on you, as a task owner. As mentioned above, You are free to pick a selection of tasks
        suggested by your mentor, though.
      </p>
    </html>
  </vertical>

  <vertical display_name="Task selection" url_name="how_when_to_pick">
    <html url_name="how_when_to_pick">
      <h3>Task selection</h3>
      <p>
        All of the tasks of OpenCraft are listed in the
        <a href="https://tasks.opencraft.com/secure/RapidBoard.jspa?projectKey=OC&amp;rapidView=5&amp;view=planning">
          Backlog
        </a>
        where it contains sections that identify groups of tasks. These sections are mainly the
        <strong>Stretch Goals</strong>
        section and <strong>Sprint Tasks</strong> sections which include the tasks we selected
        as Ready for Development under a certain sprint like the current, and the upcoming sprints.

        Tasks under <strong>Stretch Goals</strong> section are additional tasks that will be Ready for Development in
        case a developer finished his/her assigned tasks before the end of the sprint.
      </p>

      <h4>Step by step</h4>
      <ol>
        <li>Go to the <a
                href="https://tasks.opencraft.com/secure/RapidBoard.jspa?projectKey=OC&amp;rapidView=5&amp;view=planning">
          Backlog
        </a> page
        </li>
        <li>Look at tickets in the upcoming sprint, starting at the top. (Tickets are generally sorted by descending
          priority)
        </li>
        <li>
          You can use ticket color to determine which tickets to look at: If the left border of a ticket is
          <span style="color: green">green</span>, that means the ticket already has both an assignee and a reviewer,
          and so there is no need to look at it in more detail.
        </li>
        <li>
          If it's not your first sprint, try to find some tasks from projects (a.k.a. epics) that you already worked on.
          (We do want newcomers to work on different types of tasks, but some degree of continuity is also important to
          keep
          the amount of context switching sane.) Colored epic labels help with this.
        </li>
      </ol>

      <h4>Note</h4>
      <p>
        <em>
          It's not necessary to look at all of the tasks on the Backlog page to prepare for the next sprint, you just
          need to look into tasks from the upcoming sprint section to pick the set of tasks you'll be working on.
        </em>
      </p>

      <h3>When to start picking?</h3>
      <p>
        Usually the time to start picking tasks for the next sprint is in day 11 (Friday) of the current sprint,
        as most of your tasks (ideally all of them) are going to be in internal/external review and team members will be
        busy with the review process. By this time, you'll always get the chance to know how much load you're gonna be
        able
        to take in the next sprint. Check the
        <a href="http://opencraft.com/doc/handbook/process/">Process for sprints</a>
        section in the Handbook for extra details.
      </p>
    </html>
  </vertical>

  <vertical display_name="Sprint planning report" url_name="first_sprint_sprint_planning_report">
    <html url_name="first_sprint_sprint_planning_report_1">
      <p>
        Please peek at the <a href="https://tasks.opencraft.com/rest/scriptrunner/latest/custom/showOpenCraftReport" target="_blank">Sprint Planning Report</a>
        and make sure it shows the correct number of hours under "Goal" (how much time you'll have to work) for the upcoming two-week sprint.
      </p>
    </html>
  </vertical>

  <vertical display_name="Ready!" url_name="first_sprint_ready">
    <html url_name="first_sprint_ready_1">
      <p>
        You're ready! Attend your first sprint kick-off meeting!
      </p>
    </html>
  </vertical>

</sequential>
